Business and Professional Women's Club of New York State, Inc.; Records apap117
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Business And Professional Women's Clubs of New York State Inc. (BPWNYS) Records
1921-2004
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap117
3.99 cubic ft.
These records document the history of the Business and Professional Women's Clubs of New York State, Inc.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Catherine Raycraft in June 2001 and February 2002. Copies of Nike (2001-2004) were donated in July 2005.
Administrative History
The Business and Professional Women's Clubs of New York (BPWNYS) was founded in April 1919 by a group of 100 women at the Hotel Pennsylvania in New York City led by Abbie (Gail) Laughlin. Laughlin also served as the organization's first national president. The organization's first president was Adaline Zachert of Rochester, New York. The federation was to be "not just another woman's organization," but was to become, within a quarter of a century, one of the strongest sources of unified women power in the nation.[1] Originally known as the New York State Federation of Business and Professional Women's Club, the purpose of the clubs was indicated in their constitution as:
to unite organizations of Business and Professional Women in order to come to a better knowledge and understanding of their conditions and needs in different sections of the state; to secure more equitable treatment and just recognition for women in business and the professions; [and] to gather and distribute information relative to vocational opportunities and to bring about a greater solidarity of feeling among women throughout the State.[2]
The BPWNYS has been interested in achieving its goals through both state legislation and Federal enactment. The Clubs have not only made themselves felt in their respective communities but offered programs of study and action directly related to the woman in business. Since passing the Todd bill permitting women's jury service in 1937, BPWNYS has been a leader in passing much of the nation's landmark civil and women's rights legislation including: the Equal Pay Act of 1963; the Civil Rights Act of 1964; Title IX of the Civil Rights Act of 1964; the Family and Medical Leave Act of 1993; the Women's Business Ownership Act; and more recently, the Violence Against Women Act of 1994.[3] Through these, the Clubs are working on building better workplaces by focusing on equal and fair pay issues, flexible hours and parental leave, and policies for improved child and elder care.
Education has always held an important place in the Club's work. "A high school education for every girl" was one of the first goals set up to train young women for business and to help them make places for themselves in the business world.[4] Through regular meetings, BPWNYS has recognized the political, professional and personal achievements of young professional women and offered programs to provide education and guidance. Projects include the New York City Commission on the Status of Women that brings women's issues to the attention of important governmental figures, the Working Women's Clothes Closet that provides proper business attire for those who would otherwise not be able to afford business clothes, the Young Careerist Program that provides young business women and men with valuable chances to network, the Youth Leadership Program that offers workshops to high school aged girls that are designed to make them aware of available career opportunities, and Girl Scout and Business and Professional Women, a program that provides Girl Scouts with the necessary knowledge to succeed in their future careers.[5]
Scope and Contents
These records document the history of the Business and Professional Women's Clubs of New York State, Inc. The collection of BPWNYS includes the records of the state board meeting, annual legislative conference, annual state and national conventions, and publications by the Clubs. There is also a small photograph series.
The bulk of the collection is part of the Conventions and Conferences series. The records and related materials concerning the annual legislative conferences and the annual state and national conventions are extensive as is the Publications series. This series includes a run of the BPWNYS's magazine The Nike from 1951 to 2000. There are significant gaps in the State Board Meetings, Conventions and Conferences, as well as the Publication series.
For related records consult the Business and Professional Women's Club of Albany, New York (APAP-064) records.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged in the following series:
Series 1 - Administration, 1921, 1924, 1930, 1933, 1938, 1944, 1946, 1950-1951, 1960-1976, 1981-1985, 1989-1998
Series 2 - State Board Meetings, 1953, 1956-2000
Series 3 - Conventions and Conferences, 1948-1956, 1960-1977, 1979-1994
Series 4 - Publications, 1927, 1933-1937, 1939, 1944, 1948-1969, 1974-2004
Series 5 - Photographs, 1980-1990
Women; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Education; Business and Industry; Women--New York (State)--Societies and clubs.; Women's rights--Legislative histories; Businesswomen--New York (State); Labor laws and legislation--Legislative history; New York (State)--20th century; Newsletters; Publications; Minutes; Financial Records; Programs (documents); Proceedings; Annual reports; Photographs; Business and Professional Women's Clubs of New York State; New York (N.Y.). Commission on the Status of Women
- Administration, 1921-1938; 1944-1951; 1960-1976; 1981-1985; 1989-1998; 1; 0.33 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged Alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of the constitution and by-laws and annual reports of the Clubs (1960-1998). The constitution and by-laws provided the organizational structure of the Clubs. It includes printed copies of the articles of incorporation and by-laws of the National Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs (1924, 1930, 1933, 1938), certificates of incorporation and by-laws (1944, 1946, 1950, 1962, 1973), and proposed revisions to state by-laws (1967, 1974).
  The annual reports of the Clubs are similar to the histories of BPWNYS found in series 4 in that they are a chronological account of annual activities of the Clubs. The annual reports also include detailed information of various activities under the agenda or theme of each year, a photograph of the Club's president, the news of the state board meeting and annual convention, officers and committee member lists, and awards and membership reports. This series also includes documents pertaining to the projects that the BPWNYS was involved with. It includes brochures, correspondence and other documents pertaining to the BPWNYS' booth at the 1965 World's Fair, a script for a dramatic reading entitled "An Unfinished Tapestry," written by Dorothy Titchener, that tells the story of the founding of the BPWNYS, brochures and reports from "Project Buttonhole," a program designed to promote affirmative action and the handbook for the membership "Tee-Off," for recruiting new members to the BPWNYS.
  - Annual Reports, 1960-1970 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 1)
  - Annual Reports, 1970-1976 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 2)
  - Annual Reports, 1981-1985; 1989-1990 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 3)
  - Annual Reports, 1990-1998 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 4)
  - "An Unfinished Tapestry," A History of the BPWNYS, 1944 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 5)
  - Articles of Incorporation and By-laws, 1924; 1930; 1933; 1938 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 6)
  - Award Certifications and Scholarship Recipients, 1988 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 7)
  - By-laws, Proposed Revisions, 1967; 1974; 1975 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 8)
  - Certificate of Incorporation and By-Laws, 1944; 1946; 1950-1951; 1962; 1973 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 9)
  - Citations and Proclamations, 1947-1948; 1950-1952; 1973; 1982; 1995 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 10)
  - Constitution and By-laws, 1921 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 11)
  - Membership "Tee-Off,", 1965 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous Brochures, Pamphlets and Reports, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 13)
  - "Operation Buttonholes," Reports, 1963 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 14)
  - Personal Resumes, 1940; 1942; 1960; 1964-1966 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 15)
  - World Fair, 1964-1965 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 16)
- State Board Meetings, 1953; 1956-2000; 2; 1.25 cubic ft.
  Arranged Chronologically.
  This series includes minutes (with gaps), financial reports, and membership reports. The board members who have a vote are state officers, district directors, standing committee chairs, and the editor of the magazine. The state board meeting is a biannual regular meeting of BPWNYS held in September and January.
  - Minutes, 1953; 1956-1957 (Box 1 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 17)
  - Minutes, 1958 (Box 1 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 18)
  - Minutes, 1959 (Box 1 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 19)
  - Minutes, 1960 (Box 1 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 20)
  - Minutes, 1961 (Box 2 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1962 (Box 2 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1963 (Box 2 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 3)
  - Minutes and Programs, 1964 (Box 2 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1965 (Box 2 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 5)
  - Minutes and Call to Meeting, 1966 (Box 2 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 6)
  - Minutes, Programs and Call to Meeting, 1967 (Box 2 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 1968 (Box 2 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 1969 (Box 2 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 9)
  - Minutes, 1970 (Box 2 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 10)
  - Minutes, 1971 (Box 2 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 11)
  - Minutes, Call to Meeting and District Map, 1972 (Box 2 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 12)
  - Minutes, 1973 (Box 2 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 13)
  - Minutes, 1974 (Box 2 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 14)
  - Minutes, 1975 (Box 2 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 15)
  - Minutes, 1976-1977 (Box 2 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 16)
  - Minutes, 1978-1979 (Box 2 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 17)
  - Minutes, 1980 (Box 2 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 18)
  - Minutes, 1981 (Box 2 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 19)
  - Minutes, 1982 (Box 2 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 20)
  - Minutes, 1983 (Box 2 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 21)
  - Minutes and Related Material, 1984 (Box 2 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 22)
  - Minutes, 1985 (Box 2 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 23)
  - Minutes, 1986 (Box 2 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 24)
  - Minutes, 1987 (Box 2 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 25)
  - Minutes, 1988 (Box 2 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 26)
  - Minutes, 1989 (Box 2 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 27)
  - Minutes, 1990 (Box 2 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 28)
  - Minutes, 1991 (Box 2 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 29)
  - Minutes and Brochures, 1992 (Box 2 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 30)
  - Minutes and Programs, 1993 (Box 2 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 31)
  - Minutes, 1994 (Box 3 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1995 (Box 3 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1996 (Box 3 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1997 (Box 3 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1998 (Box 3 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1999 (Box 3 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 2000 (Box 3 (2-State Board Meetings), Folder 7)
- Conventions and Conferences, 1948-1956; 1960-1977; 1979-1994; 3; 1 cubic foot
  Arranged Chronologically and Alphabetically.
  Series 3 consists of the records of the annual legislative conference (with gaps), the BPWNYS annual conventions, and the national conferences held by the National Federation. State legislation committee members, and the hostess club's president, vice president, and chairs who attend these conferences each year create the annual legislative conference records. With a long and proud history of action and commitment, this conference continues to work together with the original idea of "women helping women," by supporting and initiating legislation to make a more equitable position for women in the job market. It encourages women to become involved in legislation so that they can gain power in political life in ways other than just supporting candidates, but by getting into the power structures of party politics.
  The records of the BPWNYS annual conventions include minutes (with gaps). The voting body at the annual state convention consists of the elected officers, district directors, state standing committee chairs and the duly elected delegates of the affiliated clubs or their alternates, and past state presidents. Through a convention, the Clubs encourage the greatest possible number of members to attend, and offer an opportunity to those attending to personally meet the national representative.
  The records of the national conventions that have been held by the National Federation (BPW/USA) include the minutes, financial records, and proceedings produced during the course of these conventions. The National Federation is composed of local business and professional women"s clubs from across the country.
  - Annual Convention, Minutes, 1948; 1953; 1955-1956 (Box 3 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 8)
  - Annual Convention, Minutes and Resolutions, 1960 (Box 3 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 9)
  - Annual Convention, Minutes, 1961 (Box 3 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 10)
  - Annual Convention, Minutes and Programs, 1963 (Box 3 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 11)
  - Annual Convention, Program, 1964 (Box 3 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 12)
  - Annual Convention, Minutes, Programs and Agendas, 1965 (Box 3 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 13)
  - Annual Convention, Minutes, Resolutions, Program and News Clippings, 1966 (Box 3 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 14)
  - Annual Conventions, Amendments to By-laws, Schedules of Contribution, Nike Manager Statement and Program, 1967 (Box 3 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 15)
  - Annual Conventions, Minutes and Program, 1968 (Box 3 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 16)
  - Annual Conventions, Minutes and Programs, 1969 (Box 3 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 17)
  - Annual Conventions, Minutes and Program, 1970 (Box 3 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 18)
  - Annual Conventions, Minutes and Program, 1971 (Box 3 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 19)
  - Annual Conventions, Minutes and Program, 1972 (Box 3 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 20)
  - Annual Conventions, Minutes and Program, 1973 (Box 3 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 21)
  - Annual Conventions, Minutes and Program, 1974 (Box 3 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 22)
  - Annual Conventions, Reports and Programs, 1975-1976 (Box 3 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 23)
  - Annual Conventions, Minutes and Programs, 1977 (Box 3 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 24)
  - Annual Conventions, Minutes and Programs, 1979-1980 (Box 3 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 25)
  - Annual Conventions, Minutes and Program, 1981 (Box 3 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 26)
  - Annual Conventions, Minutes and Programs, 1982 (Box 3 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 27)
  - Annual Conventions, Minutes and Programs, 1983 (Box 3 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 28)
  - Annual Conventions, Minutes and Programs, 1984 (Box 3 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 29)
  - Annual Conventions, Minutes, List of Candidates and Instruction Manual for Electing Officers and Program, 1985 (Box 3 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 30)
  - Annual Conventions, Minutes and Programs, 1986-1988 (Box 3 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 31)
  - Annual Conventions, Minutes and Programs, 1989 (Box 3 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 32)
  - Annual Conventions, Minutes and Programs, 1990 (Box 3 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 33)
  - Annual Conventions, Minutes and Programs, 1991 (Box 3 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 34)
  - Annual Conventions, Minutes and Programs, 1992 (Box 3 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 35)
  - Annual Conventions, Minutes and Programs, 1993 (Box 3 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 36)
  - Annual Conventions, Budget Information and Programs, 1994 (Box 3 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 37-38)
  - Annual Conventions, Minutes, 1997 (Box 4 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 1)
  - Legislative Conference, Minutes, 1963; 1965-1966 (Box 4 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 2)
  - Legislative Conference, Reports, News Clippings and Related Materials, 1967 (Box 4 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 3)
  - Legislative Conference, Reports and Brochures, 1973 (Box 4 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 4-5)
  - Legislative Conference, Minutes, 1976 (Box 4 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 6)
  - Legislative Conference, 1983 (Box 4 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 7)
  - National Conventions, Proceedings, 1960 (Box 4 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 8)
  - National Conventions, Minutes, Newsletters, News Clippings, Budget Information, 1964 (Box 4 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 9)
  - National Conventions, Financial Information, Reports and Programs, 1966 (Box 4 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 10)
  - National Conventions, Proceedings, 1968; 1973 (Box 4 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 11)
  - National Conventions, Financial Reports, Program and Conference Information, Newsletters, and Publicity, 1981 (Box 4 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 12)
  - National Conventions, Program, 1991 (Box 4 (3-Conventions and Conferences), Folder 13)
- Publications, 1927; 1933-1939; 1944; 1948-1969; 1974-2004; 4; 1.25 cubic ft.
  The Publications series consists of a Manual of Instructions for the BPWNYS (1958), Supplemental Manuals to the National Handbook of the BPW (1940, 1948), booklets on the history of the BPWNYS (1919-1994, with gaps), and magazines (1922-2001). The Supplemental Manual (to be used with the National Handbook) represented the combined efforts of a committee, providing an invaluable aid to local club presidents and committee chairs. The histories of the BPWNYS provide a chronological overview of the Clubs' activities since its inception. In this regard, the booklets of histories of BPWNYS are similar to the annual reports in series 1 due to the brief information they contain.
  This series also includes a group of organizational magazines that include New York State Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs-Notes (1922), Newsletter (1933-1936), one National Business Women's Week Magazine from 1939, The New York State Business and Professional Woman (1948-1952), and NIKE (1955-2001). Particularly before the publication of NIKE in 1951, many issues of publications are missing but there are enough here to give us an interesting insight into BPWNYS. This series also contains photocopies of pages from the May 1990 issue of NIKE, which is not found in hard copy in this collection.
  The group's official publications began with the New York State Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs-Notes edited by Jane J. Martin and published in July 1921. The next publication was a Newsletter edited by Miss Irene McGuire of Saratoga Springs, and the first issue of The New York State Business and Professional Woman edited by Miss Lottie Edwards and Mrs. Anne Birrell Scott of Albany and New York City was printed in magazine form with advertising in 1937. Since 1951, NIKE, the newly named state magazine, has been published. It was issued eight times a year from 1951-1954, bi-monthly from 1955-1963, and then became a quarterly magazine.
  - 25 Years of BPW, 1944 (Box 4 (4-Publications), Folder 14)
  - 50 Birthday (1919-1969) (Box 4 (4-Publications), Folder 15)
  - 60 Years of BPW, 1979 (Box 4 (4-Publications), Folder 16)
  - 75 Years of BPW, 1994 (Box 4 (4-Publications), Folder 17)
  - Facts and Faces 1919-1959, 1960 (Box 4 (4-Publications), Folder 18)
  - National Business Women's Week, 1939 (Box 4 (4-Publications), Folder 19)
  - Newsletter, Annual Report, 1927; 1935; 1937 (Box 4 (4-Publications), Folder 20)
  - Newsletter, 1933-1936 (Box 4 (4-Publications), Folder 21)
  - New York State Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs-Notes, 1922 (Box 4 (4-Publications), Folder 22)
  - The New York State Business and Professional Woman, 1948-1950 (Box 4 (4-Publications), Folder 23)
  - The New York State Business and Professional Woman, 1950-1951 (Box 4 (4-Publications), Folder 24)
  - The NIKE, Official Publication of the BPWNYS, 1951-1952 (Box 4 (4-Publications), Folder 25)
  - The NIKE, Official Publication of the BPWNYS, 1955-1960 (Box 4 (4-Publications), Folder 26)
  - The NIKE, Official Publication of the BPWNYS, 1962-1966 (Box 4 (4-Publications), Folder 27)
  - The NIKE, Official Publication of the BPWNYS, 1966-1968 (Box 4 (4-Publications), Folder 28)
  - The NIKE, Official Publication of the BPWNYS, 1968-1969 (Box 4 (4-Publications), Folder 29)
  - The NIKE, Official Publication of the BPWNYS, 1974-1979 (Box 4 (4-Publications), Folder 30)
  - The NIKE, Official Publication of the BPWNYS, 1980-1982 (Box 4 (4-Publications), Folder 31)
  - The NIKE, Official Publication of the BPWNYS, 1983 (Box 4 (4-Publications), Folder 32)
  - The NIKE, Official Publication of the BPWNYS, 1984 (Box 4 (4-Publications), Folder 33)
  - The NIKE, Official Publication of the BPWNYS, 1985 (Box 4 (4-Publications), Folder 34)
  - The NIKE, Official Publication of the BPWNYS, 1986-1987 (Box 4 (4-Publications), Folder 35)
  - The NIKE, Official Publication of the BPWNYS, 1987-1988 (Box 4 (4-Publications), Folder 36)
  - The NIKE, Official Publication of the BPWNYS, 1988-1989 (Box 4 (4-Publications), Folder 37)
  - The NIKE, Official Publication of the BPWNYS, 1989-1990 (Box 5 (4-Publications), Folder 1)
  - The NIKE, Official Publication of the BPWNYS, 1990-1991 (Box 5 (4-Publications), Folder 2)
  - The NIKE, Official Publication of the BPWNYS, 1991-1992 (Box 5 (4-Publications), Folder 3)
  - The NIKE, Official Publication of the BPWNYS, 1992-1993 (Box 5 (4-Publications), Folder 4)
  - The NIKE, Official Publication of the BPWNYS, 1993-1994 (Box 5 (4-Publications), Folder 5)
  - The NIKE, Official Publication of the BPWNYS, 1995-1996 (Box 5 (4-Publications), Folder 6)
  - The NIKE, Official Publication of the BPWNYS, 1997-1998 (Box 5 (4-Publications), Folder 7)
  - The NIKE, Official Publication of the BPWNYS, 1999 (Box 6 (4-Publications), Folder 1)
  - The NIKE, Official Publication of the BPWNYS, 2000 (Box 6 (4-Publications), Folder 2)
  - The NIKE, Official Publication of the BPWNYS, 2001-2002 (Box 6 (4-Publications), Folder 3)
  - The NIKE, Official Publication of the BPWNYS, 2002-2006 (Box 6 (4-Publications), Folder 4)
  - Supplemental Manuals to the National Handbook and Manual of Instructions to the National Handbook, 1940; 1948; 1958-1960 (Box 6 (4-Publications), Folder 5)
- Photographs, 1980-1990; 5; 0.17 cubic ft.
  Series 5 is made up of photographs, some of which are undated and unnamed of a parade, the national conventions including negative films from 1989-1990, and other images.
  - Frank C. Moore, Undated (Box 6 (5-Photographs), Folder 6)
  - Marie E. Creel, Biography and Photograph, 1980s (Box 6 (5-Photographs), Folder 7)
  - Members BPWNYS, Photographs and Related Materials, 1990 (Box 6 (5-Photographs), Folder 8)